<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fifth of November, or, The popish and schismaticall rebells. With their horrid plots, fair pretences, &amp; bloudy practices, weighed one against another: and in opposition unto both two things asserted. 1 That the supreame authority of establishing, reforming, and vindicating religion is placed in the King. 2 That religion is not to be established or reform'd in bloud.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F891A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E43_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E43[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fifth of November, or, The popish and schismaticall rebells. With their horrid plots, fair pretences, &amp; bloudy practices, weighed one against another: and in opposition unto both two things asserted. 1 That the supreame authority of establishing, reforming, and vindicating religion is placed in the King. 2 That religion is not to be established or reform'd in bloud.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Hall and W. Webb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "popish and schismaticall" are enclosed in brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>A London counterfeit edition of Wing F891. This edition has "quietnes" and "house" in the last line of the first Biblical quotation on title page, and has "Fines" at end.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 18th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The fifth of November, OR The POPISH and SCHISMATICALL REBELLS. With their horrid Plots, fair Pretences, &amp; bloudy Practices, weighed one againſt another: AND In Oppoſition unto both Two things aſſerted.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> That the ſupreame Authority of eſtabliſhing, reforming, and vindicating Religion is placed in the King.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> That Religion is not to be eſtabliſhed or reform'd in bloud.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 CHRON. 22.7, 8, 9, 10.</bibl>
               <p>And David ſaid to Solomon, My Son, as for me, it was in my mind to build an houſe unto the name of the Lord my God. But the word of the Lord came to me, ſaying, thou haſt ſhed bloud abundantly, and haſt made great wars, thou ſhalt not build an houſe unto my name, becauſe thou haſt ſhed much bloud upon the earth in my ſight. Behold a ſon ſhal be born unto thee who ſhal be a man of reſt, and I wil give him reſt from all his enemies round about; for his name ſhal be Solomon, and I wil give peace and quietnes unto Iſrael in his daies. He ſhal build an houſe for my name.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 KINGS 6.7.</bibl>
               <p>So there was neither hammer, nor axe, nor any toole of Iron heard in the houſe, while it was in building.</p>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed for <hi>H. Hall</hi> and <hi>W. Webb. 1644.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_rebels">
            <pb facs="tcp:154454:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154454:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Rebell.</head>
            <head>To the <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> Rebell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Take the boldneſſe for the preſent to put you both together; for I need not be at the charge of a ſeveral glaſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent you. If you will take the paines to look upon one anothers eyes, you may therein diſcover your own pictures. I know the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will be odious to you both, &amp; you think that none but a blind man would father this reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance. Herein you are like two women, equally famed for their deformity, yet cannot endure to be told, they are of the ſame complexion. Why ſhould you be angry, that I take notice of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, when all the world (that runs not a madding with you) ſee you ſhake hands together? I have read of waters that run unmixt in the ſame channel. What communion is grown betwixt you I know not: but your courſe ſpeaks you both, to have drawn and drunk at the ſame fountain. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of you commits a wickedneſſe ſo lewd, or broaches an Errour ſo groſſe and palpable, but can &amp; doth pretend an infallibility to warrant it. The
<pb facs="tcp:154454:3"/>Oracles of holy men inſpired were never uttered w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th more confidence and zeale, then your blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt both God and King; and both of you by murdering ſuch as are faithfull to their Church and Soveraigne, climb the ladder to your pretended martyrdome. You have divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that couple, which the Son of God came from Heaven to knit together; and inſtead of Mercy &amp; Truth, which were ſweetly met together, inſtead of righteouſnes &amp; peace which were wont moſt lovingly to kiſſe each other, your execrable practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have from time to time bin ready to betray us to thoſe fatall meetings, wherein bloud toucheth bloud. Though you be together by the eares in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, you are together by the hearts in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and rebellion; and your deſign is as good as that, which procured the atonement of Herod and Pontius Pilate. Since Liſymachus Nicanor did congratulate your offer of the right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the treachery, how ſtrangely have you (younger brethren) been encouraged? What a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe have you made ſince you walkt by the ſtaffe of his inſtructions? Me thinks the holy leagues are entred upon the Stage of England, to play thoſe parts over here which they did in France in the time of the third Henry. The ſame deſigns are here
<pb facs="tcp:154454:3"/>cloathed with the ſame pretences. Their intent was (ſaith the Hiſtorian) to incroach upon the King, &amp; to leave him nothing but a vain ſhadow of Royal authority, under the conduction and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their tyrannie; &amp; to make their way to this deviliſh deſign, the fairer, they caſt ſcandalous aſperſions upon all the Kings actions, to render them odious and intolerable. And leſt the ſmooth glaſſe of peace ſhould repreſent things in their true proportions, &amp; undeceive the people, the waters muſt be kept troubled to make them appeare (on the Kings part) crooked and diſtorted. The people are ſtirred up to oppoſe the Kings edicts of peace, and deſires of accommodation. In the interim the Leaguers goe on pretending they were for God, for the honour and increaſe of Religion, the utter extirpation of Hereſie, to preſerve the eſtate and Crown of the King, and to maintain the rights &amp; priviledges of the Subject; yet they ſwore obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the General appointed without, yea againſt the Kings commandement, and engaged their lives, honours, &amp; eſtates to adhere unto him; and all that would not aſſociate in this holy league, were perſecuted as enemies to God, rebels to the ſtate, &amp; perturbators of the publike good. I beſeech you what difference does the late Covenant bear, to diſtinguiſh it from that holy League? Are they
<pb facs="tcp:154454:4"/>not as much alike, as a bond is like an obligation? Do not therefore allow that in your ſelves, which you abominate in one another: but take notice from one anothers practices how pernitious and deteſtable thoſe principles are, that your ſeverall ſides do build upon. His Holines can give no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for murder or rebellion then John of Leyden: and what is treaſon in ſubjects that diſſent in other matters from you, is a crime of the ſame complexion in your ſelves, though your Aſſembly of Divines joyne with the remnant of your Members to Vote it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore let me expoſtulate with you in the language of the Hiſtorian. What think you to do, O you [Covenanters and] Leaguers, for God, for the faith, for the King? You undertake Arms for God, who deſires nothing but peace. You publiſh Rebellion, he commands obedience: you trouble the reſt and quietneſſe of a Chriſtian King; God willeth us to endure at the hand of a Prince al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be a Pagan: you doe it for God whoſe name you call upon, and deny the power; you do it for God who detects your actions, and knows your thoughts; you do it for God, that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found al thoſe that breed confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: you undertake wars for religion, and nothing hinders that, more then wars: you fight for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:154454:4"/>and yet you authorize blaſphemies, plant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, impiety, and deſpiſing of devotion in all places: you march under pretence of the Churches cauſe, and yet ſpoile the Clergie, and deſtroy the Churches, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You ſay t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for the King; it it be, where are his Commiſsions? if for his ſervice, where are his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements? If for him, why do you it without him? If for his obedience, wherfore do you adhere to the head of that league &amp; covenant, which is made againſt him? can you ſerve two Maſters &amp; be bound by one oath to two contraries? &amp;c. Know. you not that all bearing of Arms is treaſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kings authority? That the Subject cannot make any league without the Prince? &amp;c. Pardon me I beſeech you (ſaith he) Nobles, Princes, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, Lords &amp; Gentlemen, if I tel you that this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe which you build will be your overthrow, this fire you kindle will burne your ſelves, theſe knives you forge will be tempered in your owne intrails, and that thereby you wil leave neither of your ſelves, nor your league, but a moſt pitifull &amp; ſhameful memory. In the mean while Proteſtants will grow ſo famous for their loyalty unto every truth reveled in holy Scripture, that the very name wil be amiable &amp; had in veneration: and that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (no more ſhaken by the breath of factious
<pb facs="tcp:154454:5"/>ſpirits, then the raies of the Sun are diverted by the wind) ſhall ſtand immoveable, as a rock againſt every ſtorme from what point ſoere it bloweth. And your ſelves, when you ſhall conſider the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and conſtancie, and ſucceſſe of this Church in bearing the ſharp brunt of your malicious fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when you ſhall with a more ſad eye look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her whom you have ſo often pierced, you will relent, I doubt not. But when you ſhall ſee her in bayes, triumphing over all her enemies, when you ſhall behold her dreſt again in her ancient attire of decencie and order, wanting nothing but the neglects and nakedneſſe that are on the one ſide, and the rags &amp; ſuperfluities that are on the other ſide amongſt you, when you ſhall find her neither ſcandalous in the choice &amp; quality, nor defective in the number and proportion of her externall rites and ornaments, I am perſwaded you will lay aſide thoſe prejudices that kept you thus long from her communion, and with all alacrity caſt your ſelves into her ſecure boſome and moſt dear embracements. But if you be either Jeſuits or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, I feare (though there be nothing elſe) your obſtinacy will be a ſufficient rub in the way to your converſion, which is the onely thing makes me doubt of it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154454:5"/>
            <head>The fifth of <hi>NOVEMBER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS Day is conſecrated to the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a happy deliverance from a bloody horrible and odious act to God and man; a <hi>matter distastfull to me to remember,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Speed</hi> in the life of King <hi>James.</hi>
                  </note> or to write of</hi> (ſaith our Chronologer, <hi>that it abhorres my very ſoule to fill my pen with inke, or to blot my paper with theſe black spots of darkneſſe. A ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem invented by him, that blowes the bellowes of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; faſhioned in the forge of the hottomleſſe pit.</hi> It was the <hi>Powder-Treaſon,</hi> a plot to blow up and deſtroy at once our gracious <hi>King</hi> of bleſſed memory, with his royall <hi>Iſſue;</hi> the whole ſtock of <hi>Nobility,</hi> the glory of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and the chiefe flower of the <hi>Commons.</hi> A deſigne ſo barbarous and devilliſh, that it was able to make the earth to cremble, and the heavens to looke black with horrour and aſtoniſhment.</p>
            <p>But ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>! whilſt I ſhould purſue the flying memory of this, I am ſurpriſed by another <hi>Powder-Treaſon,</hi> which <hi>preſents</hi> and <hi>gives fire</hi> upon me. A <hi>Treaſon</hi> ſo like the former, that had not the firſt bin cruſht in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154454:6"/>ſhell, and this latter nonriſht to the growth of a great gigantine ſtature, you might very well have imagined them to be the iſſue of the ſame wombe; and however you may call them ſworne Brethren, without any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to your Judgements. They runne a great way parallel, at laſt theſe get the ſtart, by committing actuall rebellion, and out-run them. They have both the ſame <hi>place,</hi> the ſame <hi>plot,</hi> the ſame <hi>plea,</hi> for their execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſon. 1. The ſtage upon which this <hi>Tragedy</hi> was to have been acted by the <hi>Salt-peter</hi> men of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the Houſe of <hi>Parliament.</hi> The deſigne was to blow up that, and ſo it hath prov'd here. Our wiſhes for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of ſuch a <hi>Senate,</hi> were rather paſſions then prayers (as if omnipotency it ſelfe had had no other way left to reſtore and ſecure our happineſſe) and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God anſwered us (as it were) with another paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. He gave us a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as he did <hi>Iſrael</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> in his anger: And under the influence of this anger (which was more then enough to blaſt and blow up all our hopes that way) ſome of that aſſembly abuſed His Majeſties grace and clemency, they provoked him to anger too: He was driven our, and after him moſt and the moſt eminent of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> by which meanes we are deprived of the preſent benefit of all thoſe acts of grace vouchſafed by our Soveraigne, and that which ſhould have beene our <hi>Phiſicke</hi> (had all the Ingredients beene tempered together,) is become our poyſon.
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> As the <hi>place</hi> is the ſame, ſo the <hi>plot</hi> is the ſame. <hi>Their intent, when that irreligious atchievement had been performed, was to ſurprize the remainder of the Kings iſſue, to alter Religion and the Government, &amp; invade the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154454:6"/>by ſtrangers.</hi> What aimes here hath beene at an alteration you all know. The ſtandard of our <hi>publike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions</hi> is taken downe; <hi>Church-Government</hi> voted downe;
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Edward Deerings</hi> booke.</note> and it is aſſerted in print (by one that was ſometimes an eminent man amongſt them) that it was concluded, <hi>if the Lords were brought downe to the Houſe of Commons, and the King made as lowe as a Lord, the worke were done.</hi> And if their Cannon at <hi>Edge-hill</hi> or <hi>Newbery</hi> had reached the King, and cut off the two <hi>Glive branched</hi> now about his Table, what would be done with the reſt of the royall <hi>Iſſue,</hi> we may eaſily imagine. As for the <hi>invaſion of the Kingdom by ſtrangers,</hi> they have endeavoured and offered faire to make a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of it, having by Commiſſioners to that purpoſe bidden earneſt and ſtrooke hands with the <hi>Brethren of the Covenant</hi> for their advancing in upon us in a warlike manner. The <hi>plot</hi> is the ſame, the <hi>plea</hi> is the ſame too. Religion is made the ſtalking horſe to Rebellion, by both Parties. The <hi>Jeſuited</hi> and <hi>Anabaptized</hi> party rowe with the ſame Oares, ſaile by the ſame wind and compaſſe, though their coaſts be as farre diſtant as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> from <hi>Rome.</hi> They juſtifie their Treaſons and King-killing, upon the ſame grounds and pretended au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities. They are like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, though their faces looke contrary wayes, they are coupled by the <hi>tailes,</hi> where they carry thoſe fire-brands that deſtroy both Church and State; and betweene them Chriſtian Kings are crucified, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> was betweene two Theeves. The letter from <hi>Dublin</hi> of the third of <hi>October</hi> 1643. to a Member of the Houſe of Commons telleth us what <hi>precedents</hi> the <hi>Rebels</hi> now in <hi>England</hi> made for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154454:7"/>thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the words are theſe. There was a Fryar taken in the laſt expedition into <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naight,</hi> about whom was found a collection of all your votes, Ordinances and Declarations in <hi>England,</hi> very carefully peruſed and marked, with ſhort marginall notes by him, and out of them a large manuſcript, fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by himſelfe and intituled, <hi>An Apology of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of Ireland, or a Justification of their defenſive arms for the preſervation of their Religion, the maintenance of His Majeſties rights and prerogatives, the naturall &amp; juſt defence of their lives &amp; eſtates, &amp; the liberty of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by the practiſe of the State of England, &amp; the Judgment and authority of both Houſes of Parliament in England.</hi> In truth ſo unhappily penned, with ſo little variation of language, that but for the alterations of <hi>Ireland</hi> for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ſayes that letter to the Member of the Houſe) and ſome great perſons of this Kingdome in the places of ſome named by you, your owne Clerke would hardly know it from one of your owne Declarations. <hi>All that they do is for the good of the King and Kingdome. The King is truſted with the Forts, Magazines, Treaſures &amp; Offices for the good &amp; ſafety of the people; if he doth not diſcharge this truſt, but is adviſed by evil counſellors &amp; perſons they cannot conſide in, 'tis their duty ſo ſee this truſt diſcharged according to the condition and true intent therof; that they ſaw their Religion and Liberty in danger of extirpation &amp; therfore they had reaſon to put themſelves into a poſture of defence; that they are ready to lay down theſe defenſive arms as ſoon as the great Offices of the Kingdom are put into ſuch hands as they can confide in.</hi> Thus the Popiſh Rebels in <hi>Ireland</hi> fetch their Materials from theſe here in <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154454:7"/>and both <hi>Babels are built</hi> upon the ſame foundation, that hath been laid in the <hi>Votes, Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the pretended <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To returne to the <hi>Fifth</hi> of November, whence we have digreſſed; It was one of father <hi>Parſons</hi> maximes (which thoſe old <hi>Powder Traitors</hi> built upon) that <hi>if any Chriſtian Prince ſhall manifeſtly turn from the Catholique Religion, and deſires or ſeeks to reclaim others, he preſently falleth from all Princely power &amp; dignity, &amp; that before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Judge hath paſſed ſentence upon him, &amp; therupon his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are freed from al bond of Oath of Allegeance. That they may &amp; ought</hi> (provided they have a competent ſtrength) <hi>caſt out ſuch a man as an Apoſtate, heretick, backſlider and revolter from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and an Enemy to his owne ſtate and Common-wealth.</hi> Nay they goe one ſtep farther, <hi>if he favours or countenances an Heretick</hi> (put in a Malignant too, and that is any man they ſhall pleaſe to call ſo; for they will be accuſers, and Judges to in their owne cauſe againſt their Soveraigne) <hi>he preſently looſeth his Crown, ſo the King is to be depoſed, and the Pope imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to preſent unto the Kingdom for whom the people are to fight upon paine of damnation. Out of which deteſtable concluſion</hi> (ſaith our Author) <hi>aroſe the firſt ſmoake of the Gunpowder Treaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Speed ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prema.</note> And what is attributed to the <hi>Pope</hi> by the one ſide, the other with as great a freedome and confidence aſſume unto themſelves, for evidence whereof we need referre you no farther, then their <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets</hi> and <hi>Actions.</hi> The <hi>plea</hi> is the ſame. Laſtly, the <hi>meanes</hi> which they uſe to advance their deſigne is the ſame too. For their <hi>zeale</hi> thoſe prayed,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>prosper Lord their paines that labour in thy cauſe night and day Let he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154454:8"/>vaniſh away like ſmoak,
<note place="margin">Ibid</note> let their memory periſh with a crack, like the ruine and fall of a broken houſe.</hi> For <hi>caſe of conſcience, Garnett, Gerrard and Tomſon,</hi> three <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, gave it lawfull to kill innocent with nocent, rather then the ſervice ſhould quaile.</hi> For <hi>plauſibility</hi> of carriage at home, <hi>Cateſby</hi> adviſed <hi>Winter,</hi> the King might be <hi>ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by petitions to repeal the penall ſtatutes made againſt Catholicks, and to tolerate and range them among his other good Subjects.</hi> And to be <hi>plauſible</hi> abroad, <hi>Owen was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to allay the odiouſneſſe of the fact with forraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to impute the treaſon unto others diſcontentments</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">They imputed their treaſon to the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, who (to be quit) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion unto them.</note> They threw <hi>ſcandalous asperſions</hi> upon the face of His Majeſty, &amp; ſpread <hi>ſuppoſititious letters</hi> in the Kings name to their owne advantage. All which are as like the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of our times, as if the braines now on worke had forged them, or thoſe ſouls being tranſmitted into theſe bodies. But above all they are alike in their <hi>meanes</hi> of glueing and cementing their party together by <hi>Oathes,</hi> ſealing up their ſoules to a faithfulneſſe in their deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſpiracy, and tying knots upon their conſciences, leaſt they might happily have relenting thoughts, and with too much eaſe upon a ſad remorſe ſlip thorow it. But herein they differ, that theſe tranſcend them in <hi>perjury;</hi> for the obligation of <hi>one</hi> ſingle oath was to them <hi>an end of all ſtriſe:</hi> but amongſt theſe, <hi>one proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was not enough to extinguiſh or becalme their jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, their feares iſſuing from ſo extreame a guilt of conſcience betray all thoſe ſuccours, that both reaſon and religion offer, and can admit of no ſecurity. If any queſtion ſhould be made about the <hi>place,</hi> theſe may challenge the <hi>right-hand-file,</hi> as out-ſtripping them in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154454:8"/>foure or five particulars. 1. They were to act their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable villany in a <hi>Vault</hi> of darkneſſe, as it were in the ſecret tyring-houſe, as if their hearts had ſtill continued the command of a <hi>reſerve</hi> of modeſty: But theſe (as if they had made an order for the baniſhment of ſhame) play their <hi>prize</hi> upon the publike ſtage, in the view and to the reproach of <hi>Christendome.</hi> 2. The <hi>leaven</hi> of their malice had tainted but ſome few meaſures of meale: but theſe have ſpread their infection ſo farre, that a great part of two or three Kingdomes are <hi>leavened,</hi> and by this meanes the <hi>Church</hi> that bred and nouriſht them, is turned into an <hi>Acheldema.</hi> And as if all theſe were not a <hi>continent</hi> capacious enough for their bloody malice, they have poyſoned the waters too with their Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſes, that if need be, they may ſtaine the <hi>Ocean</hi> with blood, and make a <hi>red-ſea</hi> of it for their paſſage to another <hi>Canaan.</hi> Laſtly, though the <hi>Complexion</hi> of their hearts be equally <hi>ſanguine,</hi> yet theſe have hands defiled in a deeper <hi>dye</hi> of blood. They did but <hi>prime</hi> the pan: theſe have given <hi>fire</hi> in the very face of Majeſty. What thoſe did but deſigne, theſe have put in execution. And if out hearts riſe againſt ſuch as have diſcovered but an intent to butcher our friends; how ſhall we containe our hand, from them that have actually ſpilt their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood? Indeed the child of that firſt and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous conception, was come to the birth: But there was no ſtrength to bring forth. Here (I confeſſe) is more ſtrength, but it ſhall be no more then may ſerve to lengthen the paines and exaſperate the ſorrowes of their travaile. As that peece of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> might have beene <hi>their</hi> Hiſtory: <hi>Behold he travaileth with iniquity,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154454:9"/>and hath conceived miſchief, and brought forth falſhood (or a lye) he made a pit and digged it, and is ſaken into the ditch which he made,</hi> Pſal. 7.14, 15. So may the next words be a Propheſie for <hi>theſe, Their miſchiefe ſhall ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne upon their owne head, and their violent dealing ſhall come downe upon their owne pate.</hi> That Cockatrice egge which is hatched by themſelves ſhall in the end prove a ſerpent onely to themſelves; and herein I doubt not to be a true Prophet unleſſe the ſacriledge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, the luxury and wantonneſſe, the malice and ſecurity, with the pride and other crying ſinnes of this wrethed Kingdome have provoked Almighty God to marke us out for utter ruine and deſolation.</p>
            <p>I'le adde no more degrees to this odious, though moſt ſuitable compariſon: But addreſſe my ſelfe to the maintenance of thoſe two aſſertions, ſo directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt them; the firſt whereof is this, That <hi>the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream authority of eſtabliſhing,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7. v. 1. 2 Pſal. 132.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> reforming, &amp; vindicating Religion is placed in the King. David</hi> having ſheathed his victorious ſword, bethinks himſelfe of Gods worſhip and ſervice; ſorry to ſee the <hi>Arke</hi> of the Lord worſe quartered then himſelfe; he reſolves the building of an Houſe on purpoſe to lodge it in. Gods ſervice is no more circumſcrib'd by place then his own eſſence, yet it cannot be celebrated with that reverence, decency, and ſolemnity under hedges, as in a Temple. A Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therefore muſt be erected, and that ſo famous and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnificent, that it may be in ſome ſort ſuitable to his <hi>Majesty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron 22.5. and cap. 29.1.</note> who is to be adored in it. And who ſo fir to bring the firſt ſtore to this holy <hi>pyle</hi> as Gods <hi>Anointed?</hi> The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> obſerved that the King ought to be
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Politie</hi> 3.11.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154454:9"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Governour of things appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto divine worſhip, &amp; the reverend <hi>Prelates</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> addreſſe themſelves unto the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> in the language of a ſupplication to that purpoſe: <hi>Supplicamus veſtrae Majeſtati ut fidem immotam cuſtodiri ſanciatis.</hi> When God was about to build the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> (for his worſhip to be performed in) the <hi>Model</hi> was not of the peoples fancying (their blind zeale ſuffered to run a whoring, never brought forth better Religion,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.1.4. Pſ. 106.19, 20. <hi>Apud omnes Gentes, quae vis adminiſtratio ſolennes erat ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem, auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas tamen ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſanciendae, reformandae, vindicandae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis, ſemper erat penes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratum. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Iſraelitici &amp; Chriſtiani idem jus ſibive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicarunt. Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Deter. quaeſt.</hi> 19, Exod. 31.18. &amp; cap. 34.32: 34.</note> that I can read of, then <hi>Calfe-worſhip</hi>) The patterne is not to be expected from the people, nor given to them, no, nor yet to <hi>Aaron,</hi> to the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> 'tis given unto <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſupreme <hi>Magiſtrate, Exod.</hi> 25.9. So when God was pleaſed to fix his worſhip, the patterne of the <hi>Temple</hi> (that he will be honour'd in) is given to <hi>David,</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.17.19. Neither is the King a meere <hi>doore keeper</hi> in the Houſe of God: He is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabulae,</hi> the whole matter and manner of that worſhip is committed to his truſt, as well as the place wherein 'tis to be celebrated. God hath committed the <hi>Bible</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his cuſtody, not finding a ſafer place then the crown to lodge it in. The two Tables are depoſited in the hands of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he is to take care, that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part them unto the people, and ever ſince, <hi>Defenſor Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei,</hi> Defender of the Faith, hath been a Title due unto all religious Princes. To this end the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King 15.11.12. 2. Kin. 18.4. &amp; ca. 23.4.5.</note> the book of the Law, was wont to be delivered to them at their <hi>Coronation. Deut.</hi> 17.18.19.20. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.11. It is the peculiar <hi>Elogie</hi> of good Kings, in holy Scripture, to have demoliſht the high places; and deſtroyed the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154454:10"/>Idols, the perpetuall brand of evill ones, not to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſht, not to have deſtroyed them. Tis a duty ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the royall calling to ſurvey, ſettle and reforme the <hi>Church,</hi> that the people (though never ſo zealous &amp; religious) can have no <hi>Authority</hi> to that effect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. The people were never yet allowed to bee their own <hi>Carvers</hi> in a Reformation. <hi>Auferenda idola non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt quiſquam jubere privatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cont. liter. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian. l.</hi> 2. c. 92. Exod. 29.4.5.</note> ſaies S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Thou ſhalt not <hi>make</hi> to thy ſelfe any graven Image: Thou ſhalt not <hi>bow downe</hi> to them nor <hi>worſhip</hi> them, is a binding law unto all <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but to deſtroy <hi>Baal</hi> out of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment aſſigned over by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe unto the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 10.24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King 12.18.</note> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 10.28. Foureſcore arm'd with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Iehu,</hi> of the King, are enabled to root out <hi>Baal</hi> and all his worſhippers, which ſeven thouſand, that had not bowed their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> are not allowed to doe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne ſimulacra quidem falſoru Deorum, quae publice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abant, dejectaunquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egimus, niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſu, aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in libera Repub. aut Regum cum regnabantur. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. de lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 6</note> For a private man to have broken the brazen <hi>Serpent,</hi> againſt Authoritie, had not been much better then if he had worſhip'd it; for who hath required this at their hands? The people of God are often taxed for worſhipping the <hi>golden Calves</hi> upon the example and command of Idolatrous Kings: but no <hi>Prophet</hi> ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends them (though they doe for every neglect of duty in them) for not taking away of <hi>Idolatrie</hi> by force of Armes, whether the King would or not. God chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth other duties from the hands of the people, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a more private nature, &amp; is very well contented, where he findes them. They muſt <hi>hold faſt the poſſeſsion of their faith without wavering.</hi> Heb. 10.23. &amp; <hi>keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Idols,</hi> 1. Iohn. 5.21. and <hi>ſigh and mourne for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154454:10"/>corruptions of the Church,</hi> Ezek. 9.4. and <hi>ſubmit themſelves under the utmoſt penalty that authoritie inflicteth,</hi> rather then betray the truth of their Religion. So the three children did, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.18. ſo the whole race of <hi>primitive</hi> Chriſtians did under Idolatrous &amp; bloody <hi>Emperours:</hi> This is the <hi>reſiſtance</hi> we are to make with the loſſe of our <hi>owne</hi> bloud, not to the ſhedding of <hi>others, Heb</hi> 12.4. This is the only <hi>guard</hi> the Chriſtian ſtands upon, this is the beſt and moſt offenſive poſture hee puts himſelfe into for the <hi>defence</hi> of his Religion againſt that <hi>Authoritie</hi> that is ſet over him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Defendenda religio eſt à privatis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, non occidendo, ſed moriendo; non ſaevitià, ſed patientiâ; non ſcelere, ſed fide;</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactantius.</hi> He that is ſuch a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith,</hi> ſuch a Chriſtian <hi>Souldier</hi> is liſted in the <hi>noble Army of Martyrs:</hi> He is of <hi>Chriſts</hi> owne <hi>red Regiment,</hi> nay of his <hi>Lieu-guard,</hi> and ſhall have more <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance money</hi> then the reſt of common <hi>Suldiers</hi> under his ſacred <hi>banner.</hi> Tis the higheſt favour God can vouchſafe his deareſt children to draw them out and command them upon his <hi>forlorne hope</hi> for the ſervice of his <hi>Church.</hi> Hereby God does them the honour to get the commendations for their faith, and fortitude, &amp; Chriſtian reſolution. By this meanes he lets the world ſee how well they are <hi>arm'd</hi> and <hi>trained</hi> up in grace and vertue, and that they are good <hi>markes men,</hi> and <hi>good fire-men:</hi> that they ayme directly at heaven, and are fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently zealous of his glory. This is not a common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, but a peculiar favour. So the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, Vnto you it is given</hi> (not to every one) <hi>in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to beleeve on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154454:11"/>ſake. Philp.</hi> 1.29. The ſharper the fight, the more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is the Triumph. The more wounds, the more Baies. Thoſe <hi>markes of the Lord Ieſus that we carry</hi> unto heaven <hi>in our bodies</hi> with us,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.17.</note> will be our tokens, our evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences vnto a richer crowne of glory. Theſe are the duties which God hath allotted unto private Chriſtians, and expects no other from them: But if any one, or a combination a knot of them out of prepoſterous zeal, or out of an impertinent, troubleſome, and odious offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe take upon them to doe that which God hath committed to the overſight and Managery of his own immediate
<note n="*" place="margin">So the King is ſtiled. Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſter,</hi> they muſt be admoniſht to ply their own Oares: So S. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>buſie bodies,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>We beſeech you, brethren, that yee ſtudy to be quiet, and to doe your own buſineſſe.</hi> If the ſtaggaring of the <hi>Arke</hi> of Gods worſhip ſhould <hi>ominate</hi> the fall of it,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.6.7. 1. Chro. 13.9.10.</note> yet the people can pretend to no <hi>calling</hi> from God, neither can their own hands ſubſcribe them a legall <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> to ſupport it. Tis enough if their zeale can keep warme their own boſomes. Tis not expected they ſhould bee kindled into ſuch a flame as ſhould burne up all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Church. They would burne up wheat with chaffe, and good graine with tares for want of skill to diſtinguiſh them. 'Tis well if they have <hi>ſalt</hi> enough in themſelves to preſerve themſelves from being tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 'Tis well they have a <hi>Broome</hi> for their own uſe, and will take the paines to ſweep before their own doores: but let them not ſweep up their filth (as the manner of ſome is) and conceale it in private corners, nor caſt their dirt and myre into the <hi>Kings</hi> high way to defile and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154454:11"/>others. Should they attempt a <hi>Reformation</hi> againſt law, the remedie would prove worſe to <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> then the diſeaſe; for thoſe that thinke it a more ſafe and wholſome lodging to abide under the ſhadow of <hi>Authority,</hi> would aſſuredly oppoſe as well their <hi>Novelties,</hi> as <hi>uſurpation,</hi> and ſo their blood might be mingled with their fooliſh, becauſe unwarrantable ſacrifices. Should they goe about to breake downe all the banks of <hi>Government,</hi> and force open the doores of the Church to let in ſome of their <hi>Water</hi> to waſh it, whether it be the <hi>Holy</hi> water of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the ſanctified <hi>Iordan</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> This water would quickly be turned into blood, which would bee a meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and defile, and pollute the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> more then clenſe it. And thus we are entred upon the ſecond point <hi>viz.</hi> That religion is not to be eſtabliſht or reformed in blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Davids</hi> purpoſe of building <hi>God</hi> a Temple received an approbation from the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie was not upon him at that time. 2. Sam. 7.4.</note> and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſht with a promiſe <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing &amp; aſſiſtance. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.3. <hi>God</hi> laies aſide the conſideration of his own <hi>immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> and takes delight in that ſmall <hi>modell</hi> which was projected in the heart of his <hi>Annointed. Foraſmuch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as it was in thine heart to build an Houſe for my Name, thou didſt well in that it was in thine heart.</hi> 2 Chron. 6.8. <hi>Notwithſtanding thou ſhalt not build the Houſe,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>God</hi> ſerves him with a <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> or gives him a <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> to diſcharge him of this buſineſſe. He delights to dwell with him in that <hi>Temple,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> had conſecrated in his own boſome for him: but he rather confines his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154454:12"/>own worſhip to a wandering <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> then allowes <hi>David's</hi> hand in the building of the <hi>Temple.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that <hi>David</hi> himſelfe avoucheth, if you pleaſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it, you ſhall finde, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>David</hi> was a man of <hi>warre,</hi> though hee fought none but the <hi>Lords</hi> battailes. He was a man of <hi>blood,</hi> though he ſpilt very little but what was tainted and corrupted. <hi>God</hi> will not have thoſe hands engaged in the building of his <hi>holy</hi> place, which have been once engaged in <hi>blood,</hi> though thoſe engagements were juſt and of his owne warranting.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>tiam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis niſi perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> indultum eſt. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 15. &amp; 11. <hi>At ſi fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Religio, ne vera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pprimatur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>abit vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>or quod Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> fecit</hi> ibid. <hi>Idem</hi> in Epiſt. Dedic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ejuſdem operis laudat <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> 13. Clementiam in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> verba. <hi>Nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ni adſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis circa div<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſum a te ſentientibus.</hi>
               </note> The worke is reſerved for <hi>Solomon,</hi> for a King of <hi>peace. ibid.</hi> Indeed beſides Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in the <hi>Church,</hi> beſides preaching, exhortation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, caſtigation by ſpirituall cenſures, the proper duties of the <hi>Prieſtly</hi> function; there is a neceſſitie, a conveniencie at leaſt, of a <hi>Coercive</hi> power in the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> to put the ſhackles of feare and terrour upon inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and lewd men to reſtraine them. If <hi>Religion</hi> would be allowed any externall <hi>forme</hi> at all, ſhee would never be ſuffered to goe without a ſcratcht face: <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> would undermine, &amp; invade, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Church: Sinne would encroach upon holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: prophaneneſſe would aſſault and juſtle our piety, and blaſphemie would put affronts upon <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, if <hi>one</hi> arm'd with the <hi>power</hi> of the ſword did not awe men, (if not into a poſitive reſpect) at leaſt into an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive ſilence. But for the eſtabliſhing of the <hi>Church,</hi> for the propagation of the <hi>faith,</hi> for the reformation of <hi>Religion</hi> by force of <hi>Armes,</hi> by blood and violence, there is not the leaſt title in the holy <hi>Goſpell</hi> to be alleaged by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154454:12"/>way of juſtification. There are ſome in the world, that thinke to deſtroy the men is the beſt way to confute &amp; remove their errours: But we know tis no Soveraigne <hi>Antidote,</hi> that cannot expell the poyſon without the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the body.
<note place="margin">Habac. 2.12.</note> The <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> hath denounced a Woe againſt him that builds a <hi>Towne</hi> with blood, and will God have his own <hi>Houſe</hi> built ſo? If you bath the floore of the Chruch in <hi>blood,</hi> you can pave it with no ſtone ſo faire and firme, but the voice of that <hi>blood</hi> will breake through and be heard in heaven. If you paint the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Gods Church with the blood of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, they will not introduce more light, but more darkneſſe and horrour. That grand reformation of our <hi>Saviour</hi> was not brought in by the ſword, nor againſt the authoritie of the ſupreme Magiſtrate. Hee conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the world by his preaching, and by his paſſion, and eſtabliſht his own <hi>Throne</hi> in the hearts of his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> ſo as it made the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtand the ſurer. The holy Ghoſt diſtinguiſhes our Saviours conqueſt over <hi>Sinne, Satan,</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> from all other kind of conqueſts. <hi>Every battaile of the Warriour is with confuſed noiſe, and with garments rolled in blood: but this</hi> (of Chriſt) <hi>ſhall bee with burning and full of fire.</hi> Iſay. 9.5. with the ſpirit of his mouth, and the brightneſſe of his life and doctrine. And verſe 4. <hi>Thou haſt broken the yoake of his burden, and the ſtaffe of his ſhoulder, and the rod of his oppreſſour as in the day of Midian.</hi> Now if you look into the ſeventh of <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> you ſhall finde the conqueſt ſtrangely gained in that day of <hi>Midian,</hi> not with ſwords and ſpeares, but with <hi>Trumpets of Rammes hornes, and empty pitchers with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154454:13"/>Lamps in their pitchers.</hi> If our adverſaries will addreſſe themſelves into a Chriſtian courſe, let them not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Prieſts <hi>Lamps</hi> that were wont to be trimmed with the pureſt oyle. Let them not baniſh, nor impriſon the more eminent of our <hi>burning</hi> and <hi>ſhining lights,</hi> and ſo by their abſence create a darkneſſe on purpoſe, that the blinking <hi>linkes</hi> of their <hi>Levits</hi> might be ſeen to ſhine in it. Let us have the libertie to make our <hi>Trumpets</hi> ſound, and let that ſound have an equall hearing: if they can this way accompliſh it, we ſhall not envy them this advantage of their <hi>Rammes hornes and empty Pitchers,</hi> let them gaine as many <hi>Proſelytes</hi> as they can to their lewd and groundleſſe <hi>Reformation.</hi> But to goe about to make men ſull of <hi>humilitie, meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, patience, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, brotherly kindneſſe, charity, righteouſneſſe, peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt</hi> (and theſe are thoſe <hi>Evangelicall</hi> ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients that make up the conſtitution of a good <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) to attempt to make men ſuch by fire and ſword, is an experiment too apparently prepoſterous to be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull, unleſſe we think Chriſtians may be made by an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis.
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.55.</note> Are you come out, as againſt a theife, with ſwords and ſtaves to take me?</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>I taught daily in the Temple, and ye took me not.</hi> Hee that is not taken with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor hath a will to take him <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in his holy <hi>Temple;</hi> if he comes to gaine him by the ſword, the cloſe of his deſigne will be Chriſts <hi>ſhame,</hi> &amp; his <hi>crucifixion,</hi> and he hath no warrant to apprehend Chriſt in ſuch a manner, but what is ſealed by the <hi>power of darkneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.53.</note> The barbarous crueltie which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> exerciſed upon the poore <hi>Indians</hi> was ſo far from wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154454:13"/>their <hi>converſion,</hi> that it provoked them to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the God of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that would ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be adored by creatures ſo mercileſſe and bloudy, that they ſeeme to be meere ſtrangers to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, Religion can never be fruitfull in that ſoyle that is tainted and overflowed with rivers and ſtreames of bloud. A ſound faith can never be begotten by the ſenſe of feeling, when the ſtripes and prints of the nailes are made upon our own bodies. The flaming ſword was not put into <hi>Paradiſe</hi> to be an <hi>Allective,</hi> an allurement unto the tree of life, 'Tis onely the outward man, not the conſcience, that is wrought upon by compulſion. ſo that violence may be a meanes to advance <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> but can bring no advantage unto pure Religion. <hi>A pillyon</hi> and <hi>Abaddon,</hi> (a deſtroyer) are not Chriſtian names, but <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</hi> And how muche are they worſe then <hi>Iewes,</hi> that put all the innocent bloud which they pretend they have ſhed for the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of Chriſt, into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of their <hi>merits,</hi> whereas the <hi>Iewes</hi> thought it not lawfull to put the <hi>price</hi> of blood into their <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</hi> To conclude this point let <hi>Mahomets</hi> Religion be a <hi>vine</hi> that thrives beſt, and brings forth moſt grapes, when 'tis watred with the blood of thoſe that thinke her cluſters bitter. Let <hi>Ieſuits</hi> draw ſo much innocent blood from their fellow Chriſtians, as may ſwell into a <hi>River,</hi> and then let them lay the <hi>bridge</hi> of Religion over it to tranſport ſuch as are <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd</hi> (againſt their wills) to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Let <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> perſue the ſame tracke of blood to hunt after preferment for their religious <hi>Cauſe:</hi> But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154454:14"/>we have not ſo learned Chriſt. This is away to winn <hi>Converts</hi> to the Church, that true <hi>Proteſtants</hi> never yet travailed in. We are not aſhamed to profeſſe with the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> That <hi>the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but</hi> (yet) <hi>mighty through God to the pulling downe of ſtong holdes, caſting downe imaginations, and every high thing that, exalteth it ſelfe agianſt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and bringing into captivitie every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.5. The Church hath no ſword committed to her but that of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and their is no other way chalked out for her to travell by unto Heaven, but <hi>Obedience, Patience, Meekneſſe,</hi> even under the ſharpeſt perſecution, <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINES.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154454:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
